<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lavves of the market</title>
            <author>City of London (England).</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107723</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843419</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843419</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8151</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06230)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8151)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 476:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lavves of the market</title>
                  <author>City of London (England).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by [J. Windet for] Iohn Wolfe, printer to the honorable Citie of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A (-A1, blank?) B⁴ (-B4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Markets --  Law and legislation --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8151:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8151:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LAVVES OF THE MARKET.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Wolfe's device(?)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted by Iohn Wolfe, Printer to the honorable Citie of London. <hi>1595.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut illustrated border</figDesc>
               <p>I W</p>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8151:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8151:2"/>
            <head>The Lawes of the <hi>Market.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIrſt, in all the Markets of this Citie, no victuall ſhall bee ſolde, but by the price ſet by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior of this Citie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 No man ſhall foreſtall any vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall comming to the Market, as for to buy in any Inne or other priuy place, or yet comming to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, whether it be found in the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the buyer or of the ſeller, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of forfaiture of the ſame, and no Inholder, ſhall ſuffer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to bee ſold in his houſe, vppon paine of forfaiture of xl. s.</p>
            <p n="3">3 No man ſhall regrate any vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall which is in the market, or buy any victuall to ingrate in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, ſo that the commons can or may haue any part of ſuch victuall as in
<pb facs="tcp:8151:3"/> eſpeciall ſuch as be knowne for hux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or other people, occupying their liuing by ſuch victuall as they would ſo ingroſſe, vnder payne of forfayture of ſuch victuall ſo regra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: Prouided alwayes that any ſteward for any noble feaſt may buy or ingrate ſuch victuall as is conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for the ſame feaſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4 No butter ſhalbe ſold but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the waight for the time of the yeare allowed.</p>
            <p n="5">5 No Poulters ſhall deceiueably occupy the Market to ſell any ſtale victuall or ſuch as bee Poulters of this Cittie, for to ſtand in ſtraunge clothing ſo to doe, vnder payne of xl. s. and the forfayture of ſuch vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. xl. s.</p>
            <p n="6">6 No Huxters ſhall ſtand or ſit in the Market, but in the lower place and the endes of the Market to the intent they may be perfectly known
<pb facs="tcp:8151:3"/> and the ſtraunger market people haue the preheminence of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, vnder paine of iij. s. iiij. d. if the Huxters diſobey the ſame.</p>
            <p n="7">7 No vnholeſome or ſtale victuall ſhalbe ſold vnder payne of xl. s. and forfayture of the ſame victuall.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Statutes of the Streetes</hi> of this Cittie, againſt Noyſances.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, no man ſhall ſweepe the filth of the ſtreate into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell of the Cittie in the time of any rayne or at any other tyme vnder payne of vj. s. viij. d.</p>
               <p n="2">2 No man ſhall caſt, or lay in the Streetes, dogs, cattes, or other carreine, or any noyſome thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious of ayre. Nor no Inholder ſhall lay out dunge out of his houſe
<pb facs="tcp:8151:4"/> but if the cart be ready to carry the ſame away incontinently, vnder payne of xl. s.</p>
               <p n="3">3 No Brewer ſhall caſt wilfully, Dreggs, or droſſe of Ale or Beere into the Canell, vnder paine of ij. s.</p>
               <p n="4">4 No man ſhall encomber the Streetes with Timber, Stones, Cartes, or ſuch like, vnder payne of forfayture of the ſame thinge, that ſo encombreth the ſtreetes which is twenty ſhillinges fine, if hee amoue it not at the warninge of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant of the Market.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Euery buylder of houſes oughte to come to the Mayor, Aldermen, and Chamberlayne, for a ſpeciall licence for hourde of, by hym to bee made in the high Streete, and no Builder to encomber the Streetes with any manner of thinge, takinge downe for the preparinge of hys new buildinge, vnder payne of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:8151:4"/> ſhillings, except he make a hourd of xl. s.</p>
               <p n="6">6 No man ſhall ſet any Cartes in the ſtreetes by night time, vnder the payne of xij. d. and recompence to ſuch perſons as ſhalbe hurt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by if any ſuch be, xij. d.</p>
               <p n="7">7 No Budge-man ſhall leade but two horſes, and he ſhall not let them goe vnled, vnder paine of ij. s.</p>
               <p n="8">8 No man ſhall ride or driue hys carre, or carte a trotte, in the ſtreet, but paciently, vnder paine of ij. s.</p>
               <p n="9">9 No man ſhall gallope his horſe in the ſtreete vnder paine of ij. s.</p>
               <p n="10">10 No man ſhall ſhoote in the ſtreete, for wager or otherwiſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der like paine of ij. s.</p>
               <p n="11">11 No man ſhall bowle, or caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtone in the ſtreete for wager or gaine or ſuch like, vnder pain of ij. s.</p>
               <p n="12">12 No man ſhall digg any hole in the ſtreete for any matter, except he
<pb facs="tcp:8151:5"/> ſtop it vp againe, vnder paine of ij. s. and recompence to any perſon hurt thereby ij. s.</p>
               <p n="13">13 No man ſhall bury any dunge, or goung, within the liberties of this Citie vnder paine of xl. s.</p>
               <p n="14">14 No Goungfermour ſhall carry any Ordure till after ix. of the clocke in the night, vnder paine of thirtene ſhillings, foure pence.</p>
               <p n="15">15 No Goungfermer ſhall ſpill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ordure in the ſtreet, vnder paine of xiij. s. iiij. d.</p>
               <p n="16">16 No man ſhal baite Bull, Bear, or Horſe in the open ſtreete, vnder paine of xx. s.</p>
               <p n="17">17 No man ſhall haue any Kine, Goates, Hogs, Pigs, Hens, Cocks, Capons, or Duckes, in the open ſtreete, vnder paine of forfayture of the ſame.</p>
               <p n="18">18 No man ſhall mainetayne any byting Curres, or mad Dogges, in
<pb facs="tcp:8151:5"/> the ſtreetes, vnder paine of ij. s. and recompence to euery party hurte therewith ij. s.</p>
               <p n="19">19 No Cartes that ſhall be ſhodde wyth Spignayle, that ſhall come vppon the ſtreetes of this Cittie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of iij. s. iiij. d.</p>
               <p n="20">20 No Cartes vſing dayly carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age within the Cittie, nor Car ſhall haue wheeles ſhod with any Iron, but bare vnder paine of vj. s.</p>
               <p n="21">21 No man ſhall burne any ſtraw, Riſhes, or other thing, Linnen, or wollen, in the Streetes, by night or by day, vnder paine of iij. s. iiij. d.</p>
               <p n="22">22 No man ſhall blow any horne in the night, within this Cittie, or Whiſtle after the houre of nyne of the clocke in the night, vnder paine of impriſonment.</p>
               <p n="23">23 No man ſhall vſe to goe with viſoures, or diſguiſed by night, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der lyke payne of impriſonment.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8151:6"/>24 Made that Night-walkers and Euiſdroppers, like puniſhment.</p>
               <p n="25">25 No Hammar man, as a Smith a Pewterer, a Founder, and all Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers, making great ſound, ſhall not worke after the houre of nyne in the night, nor afore the houre of four in the Morninge, vnder payne of iij. s. iiij. d.</p>
               <p n="26">26 No man ſhall caſt into the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of this Citie, or the Sewers of this Cittie, without the walles, or into the Walles, Grates, or Gul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyttes of this Cittie, any manner of carryn, ſtinking fleſh, rotten fiſhe, or any rubbyſhe, doung, ſande, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, weedes, ſtones, or any other thinge, to ſtoppe the courſe of the ſame, vnder payne of cleanſing of, at his owne coſt and charge, vnder paine of impriſonment.</p>
               <p n="27">27 No man ſhal make any wided rawtes in anye of the towne Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb facs="tcp:8151:6"/> or the towne gullits, vnder paine of xx. s.</p>
               <p n="28">28 No man ſhall builde nigh the Walles of this citie, without licence of the Lord Maior, Aldermen, and Chamberlaine, vnder paine of thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing downe the ſame, and no ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence may bee graunted except that the Chamberlaine freely at al times conuenient and needeful for ingreſſe and entree, out-goynge, and cleare recourſe.</p>
               <p n="29">29 No man ſhall goe in the ſtreets by night or by day, with bow bent, or arrowes vnder his girdle, nor with ſwoorde vnſcabberd, vnder payne of impriſonmente, or wyth hand-gunne, hauinge there-with powder and matche: except it be in an vſuall May-game, or ſight.</p>
               <p n="30">30 No man ſhall after the houre of nine at the Night, keepe any rule whereby any ſuch ſuddaine out-cry
<pb facs="tcp:8151:7"/> be made in the ſtill of the Night, as making any affray, or beating hys Wife, or Seruant, or ſinging, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyling in his houſe, to the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baunce of his neighbours, vnder payne of iij. s. iiij. d.</p>
               <p n="31">31 No man ſhall make any affray vpon any Officer, which with good demeaner doth his meſſage, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of my L. Maior, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Alderman, or M. Sheriffes, or M. Chamberlain, or miſbehaue him ſelfe in any rayling vpon any Iudge of this Citie, or their Officers, which by commaundement be ſent to bring any breaker of this law and cuſtome to Ward, or to diſtreſſe, or ſuch lyke vpon payne of Impriſonment of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes, and forfayture of the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble penalty, for the offences aſſeaſing rayling vppon any Alderman, or Mayor in his office, is Iudgemente of the Pillory, rayling vpon Maſter
<pb facs="tcp:8151:7"/> Chamberlayne in his Office, forty daies impriſonment, beating, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and rayling of an officer is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, after as the treſpas is.</p>
               <p n="32">32 Memorandum that euery of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence founde in this Citty, it is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed that the Officer, a Freeman, findinge it, whiche is called <hi>primus Inuentor,</hi> hath halfe the penalty by the grace of the Court.</p>
               <p n="33">33 Alſo euery Freeman may finde any offence, but he hath no power to bring the Party before any Iudge of this Cittie, without an officer, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the party will come to his aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare by freewill.</p>
               <p n="34">34 No man hath power to arreſt, attach, or make diſtres of any goods forfitable, or offences, except the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable or Sergeant of the Maſe.</p>
               <p n="35">35 No Butcher or his ſeruant ſhal not vſe to driue any Oxe or Oxen, a trotte in the ſtreetes, but peaceably
<pb facs="tcp:8151:8"/> and if an Oxe happen to bee let goe, when hee is prepared to ſlaughter the Butcher ſhall forfayte ij. s. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides recompence, if any perſon bee hurt thereby.</p>
               <p n="36">36 No Butcher ſhall ſcauld Hogs but in the common ſcaulding houſe, vpon paine of vj. s. viij. d.</p>
               <p n="37">37 No Butcher ſhall ſell any me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell Hog, or vnwholeſome fleſh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of x. li.</p>
               <p n="38">38 No Butcher ſhall ſell any olde ſtale victuall: that is to ſay, aboue the ſlaughter of three dayes in the Winter and two in the Sommer, vnder paine of x. li.</p>
               <p n="39">39 None vnreaſonable Victuall for all manner of victuals.</p>
               <p n="40">40 No Victualer of this Citty, ſhall geue any rude or vnſettinge language, or make any clamor vpon any man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the open mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, for cheapinge of victuall vnder payne of iij. s. iiij. d.</p>
               <p n="41">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8151:8"/>41 No Butcher ſhall caſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes of beaſtes into the ſtreetes, cleaues of beaſtes feete, bones, hornes of Sheepe or other ſuch like, vnder paine of ij. s.</p>
               <p n="42">42 The Poding cart of the ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſhall not goe afore the houre of nine in the night, or after the houre of fiue in the morninge, vnder the paine of vj. s. viij. d.</p>
               <p n="43">43 No man ſhall caſt any Vrine boles, or ordure boles, into the ſtreetes, by day or night, afore the houre of nine in the night: And alſo hee ſhall not caſt it out, but bring it downe, and lay it in the Canell, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the paine of iij. s. iiij. d. And if he do caſt it vpon any perſons head, the party to haue a lawfull recompence, if he haue hurt thereby</p>
               <p n="44">44 No man ſhall hurt, cut, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy any Pipes, Seſperalles, or winde Ventes pertayninge to the
<pb facs="tcp:8151:9"/> Condite, vnder paine of impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and makinge ſatisfaction, though he doth it out of the Cittie, if he may be taken within the Citie.</p>
               <p n="45">45 No man within thys Cittie may make any Quill, and breake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Pipe of the Condite, comminge throgh his houſe, or nigh his ground, vnder payne of the Pillory, or take any water priuily vnto his houſe.</p>
               <p n="46">46 Caſting any corrupt thinge, appoyſoning the water, is Lourgu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary and felony.</p>
               <p n="47">47 Whoſoeuer deſtroy or perriſh any Cockes of the Condite, muſt haue impriſonment, and make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Old Lawes and Cuſtomes of this Cittie.</head>
               <p>No man ſhall ſet vp Shop, or occupy as a Freeman afore hee
<pb facs="tcp:8151:9"/> bee ſworne in the Chamber of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and admitted by the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, vnder paine of.</p>
               <p n="48">48 No man ſhall ſet ouer hys ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſe to any other perſon, but by licence of M. Chamberlayne, and there to be ſet ouer vnder paine.</p>
               <p n="49">49 No man which is a Forraine, ſhall not buy nor ſell within the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of this Cittie, with another Forraine, vnder payne of forfayture of the goods ſo forraine bought and ſolde.</p>
               <p n="50">50 No Freeman ſhall bee diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for to come at M. Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laynes commaundemente, to any ſummons to him giuen by any Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of the Chamber, vnder payne of impriſonment.</p>
               <p n="51">51 M. Chamberlaine hath power to ſend a Freeman to Ward, ſo that hee incontinently after ſende to the Lord Mayor, the cauſe why that he
<pb facs="tcp:8151:10"/> is puniſhed, ſo that the Lord Maior releaſe him not but by the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaines aſſent, and if he be a great Commoner, and diſobaying to the Chamberlayne, M. Chamberlayne may referre it to a Courte of Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               <p>M. Chamberlayne hath authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for to ſend or commaund any Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſe to the Counter for their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and if their offences be great as in defyling their maiſters houſes by vicious liuing, or offendinge hys maiſter by thefte, or disſlaunder, or ſuch like, then to commaund hym to Newgate.</p>
               <p>Apprentiſe enrolled, hys maiſter payeth ij. s. vj. d.</p>
               <p>Apprentice ſet ouer, hee that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth ij. s.</p>
               <p>Apprentice made free, he payeth iiij. s.</p>
               <p>Apprentiſe neuer enrolled, and
<pb facs="tcp:8151:10"/> made free, his maiſter payeth xiij. s. ij. d.</p>
               <p>A man made free by his Fathers Copy, payeth xviij. d.</p>
               <p>A Proclamation made in the time of the Mayrolty of Sir Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chell Dormer knight.</p>
               <p>An Act of Common Councell made in the Euen of Sainte Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaell, <hi>Anno Regis Henrici Octaui, xxxi.</hi> that no perſon ſhoulde lay any wares in the ſtreete, or beyonde the edge of their ſtall, vpon payne of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayture the firſt time vj. s. viij. d. the ſecond time xiij. s. iiij. d. and the third time the ware ſo layd.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
